Now look, if you've been battling an
abiding sadness that there was only one
Red Scare in the 20th century, then
baby, I got some good news for you. Yes,
there was in fact a second Red Scare
after World War II, and that's what this
video is all about. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked McCarthy
style, let's get to it. Okay, so one of
the most visible features of the Cold
War at home was a renewed campaign to
rid the United States of communist
influence, and that's what we call the
Second Red Scare. And as I mentioned at
the beginning, this was not our first
red rodeo, so let's start by comparing
the two Red Scares. you recall from unit
seven that the First Red Scare, which
occurred during the 1920s, was triggered
by a widespread fear of the influence of
communism after the Russian Revolution
had remade Russia into a communist
state. And as a result, US government
officials spearheaded many programs
intended to suppress dissent and
disloyalty among the American
population, the most extreme example of
which was the Palmer Raids. Oh, and by
the way, if you want notes guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Anyway, while the Second
Red Scare had a lot in common with the
first iteration, there was at least one
major difference. The First Red Scare
was much more broad in its scope, which
is to say those policies targeted many
different kinds of foreign radicals, and
communists were only one ingredient in
that fearful stew, even if it was one of
the most pungent ingredients. The Second
Red Scare, however, was almost entirely
focused on the eradication of communists
in the United States, and it was fueled
by the rise of communism in China and
Eastern Europe and Korea especially. And
it was a natural result of the larger
international policy of containment, on
which I flat my mouth hole prodigiously
in the last video. And in many important
ways, both Democrats and Republicans
supported the anti-communist agenda,
because rooting out communism was kind
of like an existential necessity, since
the Americans and the Soviets had metric
boatloads of nuclear weapons pointed
right at each other's faces. Even so,
over the course of the Cold War, the two
parties frequently debated the propriety
and severity of the methods that were
being used to eliminate communists from
American society. And if you want some
examples from those debated policies,
and I know that you do, then I'm going
to give you two. First of all, the Red
Scare resulted in policies designed to
test the loyalty of Americans who worked
in the federal government. So, fresh off
announcing the Truman Doctrine to the
world, President Truman signed Executive
Order 9835, which created the Federal
Employee Loyalty Program. And under this
order, a board was created to
investigate the loyalty of over 2
million federal employees and discern
whether they held any communist beliefs
or had any ties to communist
organizations. And if so, they got
canned quicker than a blue ribbon jelly
at a USDA canning competition. But to be
fair, this wasn't an entirely unfounded
hysteria. You see, Soviet spies had
infiltrated top secret programs like the
Manhattan Project during the war, which
gave Soviets vital intelligence that
facilitated their own construction of
atomic weapons. And that was a big deal,
but in truth, the board of the loyalty
program wasn't that concerned with
finding evidence of espionage, of which
there was very little, but rather
focused more broadly on rooting out
federal employees who held what they
considered dangerous political beliefs.
And eventually, similar investigative
boards were formed at the state and
municipal levels as well. And as a
result, Americans in all sectors of
society, not just federal employees,
were questioned about their potential
disloyalty. And thus, the incentive to
conform to the extreme anti-communist
ideology and policies of the federal
government became uh real intense. And
then, once Dwight D. Eisenhower became
president, he signed another executive
order targeting an even more specific
group of federal employees for
exclusion, namely gay and lesbian
Americans. It was a policy that became
known as the Lavender Scare. And here's
where I tell you that Eisenhower did not
target homosexuals because he believed
that somehow same-sex attraction
automatically made you a communist. Now
look, you guys should know that I am not
attracted to women, and as you may have
guessed, that means I am attracted to
central authoritarian economic planning,
obviously. No, it wasn't really like
that. The idea was that since
homosexuality was considered a
perversion in the wider culture, gay
federal workers were among the most
vulnerable to Soviet blackmail. In other
words, if Soviet spies were able to
determine which federal employees were
gay, then theoretically, they could
threaten to expose their secrets if they
did not cooperate with Soviet intentions
to undermine US policy, and thus,
Lavender Scare. But then, second,
federal Red Scare policies eventually
targeted the private sector as well. So,
as the panic about erasing communist
influence from the United States grew to
a fever pitch, the government extended
its investigations into those sectors
which most influence public opinion. And
as it happened, the film industry in
Hollywood, California was considered the
most fertile environment for shaping
public opinion, and therefore the
government targeted it as a hotbed of
potential communist disloyalty. As a
result, the Congressional House
Un-American Activities Committee held
widely publicized hearings investigating
many members of the film industry. And
10 of these folks, among whom were movie
directors and scriptwriters, refused to
cooperate with the committee's questions
about their political beliefs, and they
became known as the Hollywood 10. And
for their refusal to cooperate, they
were held in contempt of Congress and
blacklisted from further employment in
Hollywood. But get excited. I've saved
the juiciest and most sensational
illustration of the second Red Scare for
last, and that came in the form of
McCarthyism. So, in 1950, a Republican
senator named Joseph McCarthy gave a
speech in which he claimed to know the
names of 205 employees of the State
Department that were avowed communists.
Additionally, McCarthy claimed that the
Secretary of State knew about these
employees and continued to allow them to
shape public policy according to their
communist beliefs. So, over the next few
months, McCarthy reiterated all these
claims, all the while increasing the
number of known communists in the State
Department. And that is real scary, my
dear senator. So, let's hear it. Who are
these communists? Well, as it turned
out, McCarthy never would reveal the
names or the evidence he had to make
such accusations. And so, the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee investigated
McCarthy and found that he in fact had
no evidence for his claims, and
therefore no one should take McCarthy
seriously. And I'd like to tell you that
McCarthy, exposed in an obvious and
elaborate lie, humbled himself and
admitted his failure. But no, instead of
telling the American people the truth,
McCarthy doubled down on his claims and
began attacking the head of the
investigative committee, calling him
soft on communism. And then he went
further by denouncing this senator in
the upcoming election, and the senator
lost his seat. So, don't lose the plot
here. McCarthy was an abject liar who
made all these sensational claims in
order to prey upon Americans' Cold War
fears and center their attention on him.
And when his lies were exposed, he went
on the offensive and accused his
investigators of being soft on
communism, an attack that ultimately
cost another senator an election. And
so, this development sent fear
throughout the political community that
opposing McCarthy could have serious
consequences. And at that, McCarthy got
all kinds of drunk on his power and only
increased his fervor to root out
communism by continuing to spread lies
and unfounded claims about suspected
communists. And they were such
outlandish lies that many Americans
suspected that there must be some truth
to them since McCarthy was an American
statesman after all, and surely he
couldn't make such claims if they were
all false. But as it turned out,
McCarthy was indeed all lies, and in
1954, the edifice of his deceit came
crashing down. In that year, McCarthy
claimed that the army was full of
communists and he opened a Senate
investigation to prove it. But these
hearings were televised and millions of
Americans watched and saw for themselves
how reckless McCarthy was and how
obviously he lied. And as a result, the
Senate censured him, and while the
anti-communist policies of the Red Scare
remained in force, the McCarthyist
sensationalism of it had come to an end.
But even so, McCarthy's bluster ruined a
lot of lives because once someone was
accused of being a communist, it was
unlikely that their career would
recover. Not to mention it also locked
government policy making in a
stranglehold because lawmakers grew
exceedingly timid about introducing any
policy that could be branded as
communist. Well, okay, you can click
here to watch my other Unit 8 videos, or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brainfolds. I'm glad
you came around, and I'll catch you on
the flip flop. I'm Lear out.